Register of the Catherine Caufield papers, 1932-1996
Hoover Institution Archives
Catherine Caufield papers
1932-1996
2002C19
Hoover Institution Archives
16 manuscript boxes (6.7 linear feet)
Correspondence, notes, memoranda, reports, studies, and printed matter related to the World Bank and its effect on the economies of developing countries. Used as research material for the book by C. Caufield, Masters of Illusion: The World Bank and the Poverty of Nations (New York, 1996).
Caufield, Catherine.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2002.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1981 Author, The Man Who Ate Bluebottles: And Other Great British Eccentrics
1984 Author, In the Rainforest: Report from a Strange, Beautiful, Imperiled World
1989 Author, Multiple Exposures: Chronicles of the Radiation Age
1996 Author, Masters of Illusion: The World Bank and the Poverty of Nations
Scope and Content of Collection
The Catherine Caufield papers contain correspondence, notes, memoranda, reports, studies, and printed matter related to the World Bank and its effect on the economies of developing countries.
Catherine Caufield was a British author and journalist who served as an environmental correspondent for New Scientist. The collection consists of Caufield's research files for Masters of Illusion: The World Bank and the Poverty of Nations, a book which was critical of the World Bank. In addition to printed matter, correspondence, and Caufield's notes, the collection includes internal World Bank documents, such as memoranda and reports.
World Bank.; Developing countries.; Economic assistance.
- Africa, 1985-1994 (Box-folder 1: 1-3)
- Agriculture, 1994 (Box-folder 1: 4)
- Alternatives, 1991-1996 (Box-folder 1: 5)
- Appraisal and design, 1991-1995 (Box-folder 1: 6)
- Asia, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 1: 7)
- Asian tigers, 1979-1994 (Box-folder 1: 8)
- Bangladesh, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 1: 9)
- Bangladesh (cont'd.), 1992-1993 (Box-folder 2: 1)
- Board, 1989-1996 (Box-folder 2: 2)
- Brazil, 1989-1995 (Box-folder 2: 3)
- [Brazil and Guatamala], 1985-1993 (Box-folder 2: 4)
- Bureaucracy and management, 1987-1995 (Box-folder 2: 5)
- Capital flight, 1983-1995 (Box-folder 2: 6)
- Columbia, 1972-1992 (Box-folder 2: 7)
- Columbia, (cont'd.), 1972-1992 (Box-folder 3: 1)
- Consultants, 1977-1994 (Box-folder 3: 2)
- [Conable] and environment, 1992-1995 (Box-folder 3: 3)
- Corruption and oversight, 1992-1995 (Box-folder 3: 4)
- Cost-benefit and environmental accouting, 1991-1994 (Box-folder 3: 5)
- Dams, 1989-1996 (Box-folder 3: 6)
- Debt (1990s), 1992-1995 (Box-folder 3: 7)
- Debt crisis, 1974-1994 (Box-folder 4: 1-3)
- Development Theory, 1945-1990 (Box-folder 4: 4)
- Disbursement and procurement, 1991-1996 (Box-folder 4: 5)
- [Eastern Europe], 1993, undated (Box-folder 4: 6)
- Education, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 4: 7)
- [Electric] projects, 1958-1971 (Box-folder 5: 1)
- Energy, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 5: 2)
- Environment, 1990-1996, undated (Box-folder 5: 3)
- Evaluation, 1976-1994 (Box-folder 5: 4-5)
- False appraisals, 1988-1993 (Box-folder 5: 6-7)
- Fiftieth anniversary, 1992-1995 (Box-folder 6: 1)
- Financial conditions and credit worthiness, 1962-1971, undated (Box-folder 6: 2)
- Forestry, 1991, undated (Box-folder 6: 3)
- Foreign bonds, 1932, 1988 (Box-folder 6: 4-5)
- Free trade, 1986-1995 (Box-folder 6: 6-7)
- Fundraising, 1988-1995 (Box-folder 7: 1)
- Global Environment Facility (GEF), 1991-1995 (Box-folder 7: 2)
- Governance, 1991-1995 (Box-folder 7: 3-4)
- Green Revolution and [nutrition], 1983-1993 (Box-folder 7: 5-6)
- Gross National Product and indices, 1991-1995 (Box-folder 8: 1)
- Guinea forestry, 1993 (Box-folder 8: 2)
- Health and nutrition, 1990-1995 (Box-folder 8: 3)
- Indebtedness of [borrowers], quality of Bank's loan portfolio, 1987-1995 (Box-folder 8: 4)
- India, structural adjustment loans, 1985-1995 (Box-folder 8: 5)
- Indigenous, 1986-1993 (Box-folder 8: 6)
- Irrigation, 1984-1993 (Box-folder 8: 7-8)
- Karjan, 1987-1994 (Box-folder 8: 9)
- Latin America, 1990-1994 (Box-folder 9: 1)
- Lending statistics, 1949-1993 (Box-folder 9: 2)
- [McN] projects, 1978-1994 (Box-folder 9: 3)
- Mexico, 1987-1996 (Box-folder 9: 4-6)
- Missions and consultants, 1986-1993 (Box-folder 9: 7)
- Narmada, 1992-1996 (Box-folder 9: 8)
- Narmada (cont'd.), 1992-1996 (Box-folder 10: 1-2)
- Non-governmental organizations (NGOs) and public participation, 1987-1994 (Box-folder 10: 3)
- Political influence, 1981-1994 (Box-folder 10: 4)
- Ponzi, pressure to lend, 1982-1996 (Box-folder 10: 5-6)
- Population, 1981-1995 (Box-folder 11: 1-2)
- Preston, Lewis, 1991-1996 (Box-folder 11: 3)
- Private enterprise, 1989-1996 (Box-folder 11: 4)
- Projects
  - 1980s projects, 1985-1994 (Box-folder 11: 5)
  - Good projects, alternatives, 1991-1996 (Box-folder 11: 6)
  - Recent projects, 1993-1995 (Box-folder 11: 7)
- Public relations, 1993-1995 (Box-folder 12: 1)
- Resettlement, 1988-1994 (Box-folder 12: 2)
- Revolving door, undue influence, 1991-1993, undated (Box-folder 12: 3)
- Secrecy, 1993-1996 (Box-folder 12: 4)
- Singrauli, 1979-1994 (Box-folder 12: 5-7)
- Slums, Dharavi, 1987-1994 (Box-folder 13: 1)
- Social, 1992-1995 (Box-folder 13: 2)
- Staff, undated (Box-folder 13: 3)
- State enterprises, 1981-1995 (Box-folder 13: 4-5)
- Structural adjustment loans, prehistory, 1971-1995 (Box-folder 13: 6)
- Technocrats, 1950-1962, undated (Box-folder 13: 7)
- Trends, undated (Box-folder 13: 8)
- Turkey, 1994 (Box-folder 13: 9)
- Upper Indravati, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 14: 1)
- Urban, 1985-1993 (Box-folder 14: 2-3)
- Wapenhans, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 14: 4)
- Water supply, 1985-1994 (Box-folder 14: 5)
- Women, 1993-1995 (Box-folder 14: 6)
- Women and adjustment, 1991, undated (Box-folder 14: 7)
- Woods, George, 1968-1994 (Box-folder 14: 8)
- World Bank
  - Annual reports and loans, 1949-1994 (Box-folder 15: 1-6)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes reports detailing loan amounts
  - Annual reports and loans (cont'd.), 1949-1994 (Box-folder 16: 1)
  - Research, 1991-1995 (Box-folder 16: 2)
  - Soundness, 1989-1996 (Box-folder 16: 3)
  - Special legal status (bossy bank), 1979-1995 (Box-folder 16: 4-5)
- Volta Dam, 1961-1990 (Box-folder 16: 6)
- Yacyretá, 1991-1995 (Box-folder 16: 7)
- Yanhee, 1957-1995 (Box-folder 16: 8)